Guide to the Records of the James Arthur Collection of Clocks and Watches RG.42.1
New York University Archives
Records of the James Arthur Collection of Clocks and Watches
1740-1982
1931-1963
New York University Archives
Arthur, James, 1842-1930
RG.42.1
5.28 Linear Feet in 3 manuscript boxes, 2 half manuscript boxes, and 2 free-standing grandfather clocks
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Appraisal
The records of the James Arthur Collection of Clocks and Watches were housed with the "Archives H" collection of the University Archives; no accession data is available. Several folders of related material (3 inches) were transferred from the office of the Dean of Libraries in December 1984, and incorporated with the records from Archives H. Fifteen feet of material on the Arthur Collection is on deposit at the Smithsonian Institution. The Arthur book collection remains at the University and is housed in the Special Collections Department of Bobst Library. Although the records cover an extensive time period, 1926-1982, they are not complete.
Materials separated from the collection include photographs (see separation sheet) and 28 items (newspaper clippings and Thermofax copies) which were photocopied on acid-free paper. Additional conservation measures taken were the removal of staples and paper clips and replacement with plastic clips when necessary.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in five series:
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: Financial Statements
Series III: Reports from Curators and Report Summaries
Series IV: Grandfather Clocks, and
Series V: Photographs.
Series I-IV are arranged chronologically, while materials in Series V are arranged in the order in which they were found.
Biography of Arthur Lionel Rawlings
Dr. Arthur Lionel Rawlings is listed as the first curator of the Museum, a position he held from 1956 until his death in 1959. (The Arthur Collection had had specific curators before 1956.) Before his appointment as curator, Rawlings served as the head of special products at the Bulova Research and Development Labs in Woodside, Queens. A native of England, Rawlings attended university in Birmingham and London and held many patents on gyro-compasses, gyroscopic stabilization, and fire-control devices. He wrote several books, including the then-standard works The Theory of the Gyro Compass and Science of Clocks and Watches. Previous employers included Sperry Gyroscope, Ltd., the Scientific Research Branch of the British Admiralty, and the U.S. Time Corporation. He also served as president of the Horological Society of New York and was a member of the National Association of Watch and Clock Collectors.
Dr. Rawlings also gave one of the Arthur-funded lectures on May 15, 1953, on the following topic: "From Hours to Microseconds: Three Centuries of Timekeeping Progress, 1650-1950."
An obituary for Dr. Rawlings from the Long Island Star-Journal from November 18, 1959, indicates that he passed away after suffering a heart attack while driving on the Van Wyck Expressway on November 17. He was 78.
History of the Watch and Clock Museum
Per an October 31, 1956, NYU press release, the Watch and Clock Museum was established in that year from the materials in three collections of timepieces then owned by the University. Over half the materials came from the James Arthur Collection of Clocks and Watches, which had been administered by the University since the 1930s.
The Museum was housed in the Gould Memorial Library at NYU's University Heights campus. With over 3,000 timepieces, the Museum was touted as the largest horological collection in the Western Hempisphere at the time of its establishment.
The Arthur Collection included books and research materials, as well as an endowment for the upkeep of the collection and a periodic lecture series on the topic of "time and its mysteries." The money did not prove sufficient for the upkeep and administration of such a varied and difficult collection (some of the timepieces dated from the 16th century). Without the proper resources to reassemble the timepieces and without a sufficient display method, when the University Heights campus closed in 1973 and NYU relocated to Greenwich Village the artifacts were placed on permanent loan to the Smithsonian Institution in Washington, D.C. The books from the Arthur Collection were transferred to the University's rare books collection, and the records and photographs of the collection remained with the University Archives.
In 1982 New York University decided to dispose of the Arthur Collection, dividing the items between The Smithsonian Institution, the Time Museum at Rockford, and the NAWCC Museum at Columbia, Pennsylvania but has retained the records of the collection.
In 1985 the Smithsonian transferred the timepieces to the National Watch and Clock Museum in Columbia, Pennsylvania. In 2006, six of the timepiecse from the collection were sold at auction. More information may be found at the museum's website: http://www.nawcc.org/collections.
Biography of James Arthur
James Arthur was born February 26, 1842, in Crosscandley, Ireland. As a boy he studied mechanics and developed an interest in horology. In 1871 he emigrated to New York where in 1885 he founded Arthur and Co., manufacturers of mechanical models for inventors and devices such as differential gears for automobiles.
Arthur's spare time was spent collecting and designing and making clocks and watches. In 1925, at the suggestion of his son-in-law, Irving H. Berg, Chaplain of New York University (1919-1936), and later Dean of University College (1936-1941), Arthur presented his collection of 300 clocks, more than 1500 watches and books to New York University. Accompanying the gift was an endowment of $110,000 to support a series of lectures on "time and its mysteries", to keep the collection in a state of repair and to provide for new acquisitions. Arthur stipulated that none of the income was to be used to pay curators.
James Arthur died in Winsted, Connecticut on April 27, 1930.
For more detailed biographical information see The National Cyclopaedia of American Biography, Volume XXXI, page 232, published by James T. White & Company, New York, 1944.
James Arthur Lectures - Time and Its Mysteries
April 29, 1932 Time Robert Andrews Millikan, Ph.D., Sc.D., LL.D. California Institute of Technology
May 4, 1933 Time and Change in History John Campbell Merriam, Ph.D., Sc.D., LL.D. Carnegie Institution of Washington
February 6, 1934 On the Lifetime of a Galaxy Harlow Shapley, Ph.D., Sc.D., Litt.D., LL.D. Harvard University
May 16, 1935 The Beginnings of Time Measurement and the Origins of Our Calendar James Henry Breasted, Ph.D., Litt.D., LL.D. The Oriental Institue, The University of Chicago
April 2, 1936 The Time Concept and Time Sense Among Cultured and Uncultured People Daniel Webster Hering, Ph.D., C.E., LL.D. New York University
April 9, 1937 What Is Time? William Francis Gray Swann, A.M., Sc.D. Bartol Research Foundation of Franklin Institute
April 21, 1938 Time and Individuality John Dewey, Ph.D., LL.D. Columbia University
April 26, 1939 Time and the Growth of Physics Arthur H. Compton, Ph.D., Sc.D., LL.D.\ The University of Chicago
April 16, 1941 The Geologic Records of Time Adolph Knoph, Ph.D. Yale University
April 16, 1946 Time and Historical Perspective James T. Shotwell, Ph.D., LL.D. Columbia University
April 7, 1949 Developments in Portable Timepieces George P. Luckey, A.M. Hamilton Watch Company
October 17, 1951 The Early American Clockmaking Industry Brooks Palmer, A.B. National Association of Watch and Clock Collectors
May 15, 1953 From Hours to Microseconds: Three Centuries of Timekeeping Progress, 1650-1950 Arthur Lionel Rawlings, Ph.D. Bulova Research and Development Laboratories
March 14, 1958 Astronomical Time and Atomic Time William Markowitz, Ph.D. Director of the Time Service Division United States Naval Observatory
May 14, 1960 The Astronomical Scale Henry Norris Russell, Ph.D. Princeton University
February 18, 1969 The Hypothesis of Environmental Timing of the Clock Frank A. Brown, Jr. Morrison Professor of Biology Northwestern University
March 4, 1969 The Cellular-Biochemical Clock Hypothesis J. Woodland Hastings Harvard University What was presumably the content of these lectures was publics as follows: "The Biological Clock, Two Views" by Frank A. Brown Jr., J. Woodland Hastings and John D. Palmer, New York, Academic Press [1970]
1972 Physics at the Origin of Time R. Omnes Laboratories de Physique Theoretique et Hautes Energies University de Patis-Sud, Orsay, France
1972 Physics at the Origin of Time Steven Frautschi California Institute of Technology These lectures appear to have been published in "Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences," Vol. 224, pp 339-54 and pp 355-64
April 16, 1975 Time and the Atom: Precise Measurement of Time with Atomic Clocks Norman F. Ramsey Higgins Professor of Physics Harvard University
April 17, 1975 Molecular Beam Spectroscopy with Molecules, Atoms, and Neutrons Norman F. Ramsey Higgins Professor of Physics Harvard University
October 17, 1978 Time Without End: Physics and Biology in an Open Universe General Survey Freeman J. Dyson Professor of Physics The Institute for Advanced Study
October 19, 1978 Time Without End: Physics and Biology in an Open Universe Technical Details Freeman J. Dyson Professor of Physics The Institute of Advanced Study
November 13, 1980 Reality, Illusion and Time John Archibald Wheeler Ashbel Smith Professor of Physics University of Texas at Austin
November 14, 1980 Time and Light John Archibal Wheeler Ashbell Smith Professor of Physics University of Texas at Austin
November 17, 1980 Beyond the End of Time John Archibald Wheeler Ashbell Smith Professor of Physics University of Texas at Austin
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of records of the curators and University officers related to the administration of the James Arthur Collection of Clocks and Watches, as well as the lecture series "Time and Its Mysteries." This collection also contains photographs documenting James Arthur's clock and watch collection.
The bulk of the materials in this collection date from 1931 to 1963, the year the clocks and watches were sent on permanent loan to the Smithsonian Institution. The records are incomplete with many gaps.
This collection will be of value for answering queries about the history and disposition of the James Arthur Collection although it does not contain much information on the specific clocks and watches themselves. The records also document the University's venture into maintaining a museum and its eventual decision to discontinue this effort.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials found in Series V: Photographs were transferred from the New York University Archives Photograph Collection (PHOTO 00001) in May 2024. The accession number associated with this accretion is 2024.030.
James Arthur Collection of Clocks and Watches List of Curators
Daniel Webster Hering - first curator; served until his death on March 24, 1938
Carlos da Zafra - resigned March 1946
John M. Labberton - April 1946 - June 1950
Edward C. Smith - September 1, 1950 - ?
Arthur Lionel Rawlings - September 1, 1956 - November 17, 1959
Brooks Palmer - Associate Curator - September 1, 1956 - February 1960; Curator February 1960 - ?
The records include information on the clock and watch collection and on the lecture series, "Time and Its Mysteries". The arrangement of the materials found in Archives H and in the office of the Dean of Libraries was chronological; papers from these two sources have been interfiled.
Clocks and watches |x History.; Financial statements.; Lectures and lecturing.; Clocks and watches.; Clocks and watches |v collections and collecting.; Correspondence.; Tall case clocks.; Photographs.; da Zafra, Carlos; Hering, D.W. (Daniel Webster), 1850-1938; Rawlings, A.L. (Arthur Lionel); Palmer, Brooks; Labberton, J. M. (John Madison), 1893-; Smith, Edward C.
- Series I: Correspondence, 1926-1982; 0.88 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains an excerpt from James Arthur's will donating his collection to the University (see Box 1, Folder 2); correspondence and reports of the curators and University officers related to the administration of both the collection and the series of lectures on "Time and its Mysteries;" minutes of the faculty advisory committee; publicity materials for the collection and lectures; and newspaper clippings.
  The lectures were held annually until the outbreak of World War II. There is a gap in the collection from 1942 until 1946. Thereafter, lectures were held at intervals from two to four years with the most recent one in 1978. New York University Press published the first twelve lectures in a three volume series entitled "Time and Its Mysteries." Materials in the collection related to the lectures often include biographical information on the speakers, printed programs and the texts of the lectures. A list of the lectures is included in the finding aid.
  Information on the clock and watch collection can be found in correspondence and reports of the curators. There is no complete inventory of the clocks, but in 1932 Daniel Webster Hering, the first curator, published "The Lure of the Clock," which illustrated and described some items in the original collection. The problems of housing and administering the collection, which are evident throughout the correspondence, finally led to the transfer of the collection to the Smithsonian Institution in September 1963. Although the collection contains correspondence with a Smithsonian official (see Box 2, Folder 19), the agreement is not in the collection. Box 2, Folder 31 contains a list of clocks that remain at the University.
  Little information is available on the book collection save a listing of the books in Box 2, Folder 20.
  A list of the curators is included in the finding aid.
  Correspondence.; Arthur, James, 1842-1930
  - 1926 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1927 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1928 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1929 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1930 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1931 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1932 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1933 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1934 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1935 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1936 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1937 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1938 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1939 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1940 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1941 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1946 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1947 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1948 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1949 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1950 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1951 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1952 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 1953 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1954 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 1955 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 1956 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 1957 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 1958 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 1959 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - 1960 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - 1961 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - 1962 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - 1963 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - 1964 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - 1966 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - 1969 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - 1970 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - 1971 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - 1972 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - 1973 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - 1975 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - 1977 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - 1978 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - 1980 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - 1981 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - 1982 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Series II: Financial Statements, 1941-1961; 0.23 Linear Feet in 1 half manuscript box
  This series consists of financial statements dating from 1941-1961. This series contains reports of income and expenditures from the endowment account. Reports include information on new acquisitions to the clock collection.
  Arthur, James, 1842-1930
  - 1941-1961 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Series III: Reports from the Curator and report summaries, 1927-1937; 0.23 Linear Feet in 1 half manuscript box
  This series includes reports prepared by curator D.W. Hering and issued by the New York University Bureau of Public Information, with report summaries. This series also includes a checklist of items included in a special exhibition of materials from the clock and watch collection in 1951.
  Hering, D.W. (Daniel Webster), 1850-1938; Arthur, James, 1842-1930
  - Reports - Sept. 1927 (2 copies); July, 1928; March, 1929 (2 copies), 1927-1929 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Reports - May, 1930 (2 copies); Nov., 1930 (2 copies); April, 1931 (2 copies); Nov. 1933 (2 copies), 1930-1933 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Summaries - 1927, 1936, 1937; checklist of clocks included in the Special Exhibition of American clocks, Feb. 9-16, 1951; also includes letter to the James Arthur Foundation, Dec. 31, 1936 from D. W. Hering., 1927-1951 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Series IV: Grandfather Clocks, mid 1700s, undated; 2 item two tall case clocks
  - Grandfather clock, Undated; cuid462; 1 item one tall case clock (Item RG.42.1.cuid462)
    Tall case clocks.
  - Grandfather Clock, mid 1700s; cuid18369 (Item RG.42.1.cuid18369)
    This item in the James Arthur Watch and Clock Collection consists of an 18th century grandfather clock built by Pennsylvania cabinetmaker Isaac Thomas that formerly belonged to the family of Abraham Lincoln's Secretary of War, Edwin M. Stanton.
- Series V: Photographs, 1926-1956; 0.44 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box
  The photographs in this series depict James Arthur's clock and watch collection.The clocks photographed include table top clocks, grandfather clocks, juke box clocks, decorative clocks of varying sizes, and pocket watches. This series features photographs of Assistant Dean W.R. Bryan of NYU's former College of Engineering; the Clock Museum located at NYU's former University Heights campus; and of the Clock Museum's curators Daniel Webster Hering, Carlos de Zafra, and Edward C. Smith.
  - William R. Bryan (Assistant Dean) with J. Arthur Collection, 1953-1956 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
  - CBS Publicity Radio Show -- "The World's Oldest Household Clock" for "Death Knell", 1939 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Photographs from Lectures, 1926-1927, 1936, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
  - Clock Museum at University Heights, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Curators: Daniel Webster Hering, Carlos de Zafra, and Edward C. Smith, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 8)